<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Monte Carlo on Post It!</title>
    <link>http://brunettoziosi.eu/tags/monte-carlo/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Monte Carlo on Post It!</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 15 Mar 2012 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://brunettoziosi.eu/tags/monte-carlo/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>PhD question #3: Monte Carlo Markov chain</title>
      <link>http://brunettoziosi.eu/posts/phd-question-3-monte-carlo-markov-chain/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Mar 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brunettoziosi.eu/posts/phd-question-3-monte-carlo-markov-chain/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.brunettoziosi.eu/blog/wordpress/phd-question-1-latexm_latex/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; title=&#34;PhD question #1: M*&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.brunettoziosi.eu/blog/wordpress/phd-question-2-spherical-collapse/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; title=&#34;PhD question #2: spherical collapse&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, in this post I write about the Monte Carlo Markov chain. This post is the Wordpress transposition of a page in my private and local Mediawiki installation, so maybe has not a perfect structure and look&amp;amp;feel. Also, the Latex formulas embedded in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/MediaWiki&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; title=&#34;Mediawiki homepage&#34;&gt;Mediawiki&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://wordpress.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; title=&#34;Wordpress homepage&#34;&gt;Wordpress&lt;/a&gt; look horrible.&lt;br /&gt;
Most of this post is made by paragraphs from &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; title=&#34;Wikipedia homepage&#34;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt; and from &lt;a href=&#34;http://arxiv.org/abs/0712.3028&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; title=&#34;Licia Verde&#39;s article page&#34;&gt;A practical guide to Basic Statistical Techniques for Data Analysis in Cosmology&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&#34;http://icc.ub.edu/~liciaverde/Home%20Page.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; title=&#34;Licia Verde homepage&#34;&gt;Licia Verde&lt;/a&gt; that I rearranged or try to explain and summarize.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essentially you can think a Markov chain as a set of states of physical system, or a series of values, depending on some parameters, in which every step/status depends only on the present status and not on the past. A Monte Carlo Markov chain is a Markov chain that proceeds trying random steps and tends to converge to an equilibrium that should be the best set of parameters we are looking for.&lt;br /&gt;
To improve performances and precision usually more chains are used, starting from different and well-separated points, for a single estimation and a convergence criterion define when to stop.&lt;br /&gt;
The steady state, or the equilibrium distribution, if it exists, roughly is the combination of parameters, o the vector for the probabilities to be in one status, that emerge to be constant in the long term. This means that if the system (the chain) at some time has a probability vector &lt;code&gt;$q$&lt;/code&gt; for the next status, it will have probability vector &lt;code&gt;$q$&lt;/code&gt; forever. &lt;code&gt;$q$&lt;/code&gt; is an eigenvector of the transition matrix with eingenvalue 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>