<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Opinion on Post It!</title>
    <link>http://brunettoziosi.eu/tags/opinion/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Opinion on Post It!</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 07 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://brunettoziosi.eu/tags/opinion/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>What do you think about me?</title>
      <link>http://brunettoziosi.eu/posts/what-do-you-think-about-me/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brunettoziosi.eu/posts/what-do-you-think-about-me/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;AKA &amp;ldquo;In 150 characters or fewer, tell us what makes you unique. Try to be creative and say something that will catch our eye!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These days I am struggling trying to (re)write a thesis decent enough to get a &lt;a href=&#34;../../pages/research/phd/&#34;&gt;PhD&lt;/a&gt;
and different enough from my point of view to be accepted by my supervisor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time I am applying to an increasing number of jobs possibly matching
my love for data exploration/visualization and programming. And no, I am (almost) not applying
for post-docs anymore. It is a waste of time.&lt;br /&gt;
However, every average job or post-doc application requires you to advertise yourself
as much as possible so that your future employer can purchase you and be satisfied with his choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have read at least a pair of posts on this site (or a piece of my thesis),
it would be obvious to you that writing is not among my very few qualities.
And, as a result of my education, self-confidence and being proud of myself aren&amp;rsquo;t there either.
On top of that, it is always difficult to have a fair opinion and to see what others
see about ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today a friend of mine was so kind to send me few words to describe me. They were amazingly
accurate:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tendenzialmente brontolone e negativo, riesco meglio ad esprimere quello penso
e sono attraverso un codice che non a parole&amp;hellip;
Sempre alla ricerca di nuovi stimoli, che siano un nuovo linguaggio di programmazione,
una nuova app, o semplicemente una luce diversa con cui scattare una foto,
non lasciatemi troppo a me stesso che mi deprimo, ma se debitamente sostenuto
sono capace di grandi cose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(&lt;em&gt;Basically grumpy and negative, I can express what I think and what I am better by coding than
with words&amp;hellip; Always looking for new ideas, either a new programming language,
a new app or simply a different light for a photo.
Don&amp;rsquo;t leave me alone too much with myself because I&amp;rsquo;ll get down, but if
properly supported I can do great things.&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Thanks &lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/102539794582678678803/about&#34;&gt;Valentina&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stsci.edu/~calvi/calvi/aboutme.html&#34;&gt;C.&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is really inspiring and helpful, thus, please, give me your &amp;ldquo;150 or fewer&amp;rdquo; (or more) words about
me in the comments below!! Of course, this is an attempt to build a constructive discussion, so, please,
don&amp;rsquo;t be stupid, aggressive or impolite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;b.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>