<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>brunetto's blog (Python)</title><link>brunetto.github.io</link><description>This is a demo site for Nikola.</description><lastBuildDate>Sun, 18 Aug 2013 01:44:41 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>nikola</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Python logging</title><link>brunetto.github.io/posts/python-logging.html</link><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;After I had a &lt;a href="http://brunettoziosi.blogspot.it/2011/11/python-parallel-job-manager.html" target="_blank" title="Python parallel job manager"&gt;Python parallel job manager&lt;/a&gt; I realize that all the attempts I have done to log what happen in my code weren't satisfying. It was not comfortable to manage every output when I want to change something and it was impossible to switch off some of logs without changing the code. The Python logging library is a great piece of code that permits to personalize most of the aspect of the logging in a program but maintaining a standard and comfortable interface. It also allows an easy management of many different outputs (file, screen, ...) and different levels of logging (error, info, ...) indipendent one from each other. It also allows to handle the logging of the imported modules.  &lt;br&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/posts/python-logging.html"&gt;Read more...&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>code</category><category>Python</category><guid>brunetto.github.io/posts/python-logging.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 17 Nov 2011 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Python CLI and configuration file parser</title><link>brunetto.github.io/posts/python-cli-and-configuration-file-parser.html</link><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;One of the first things I needed writing the code for my thesis was the ability to read options and parameters both from a configuration file and from the command line. After some attempts I have found (at &lt;a href="http://www.decalage.info/" target="_blank" title="http://www.decalage.info"&gt;http://www.decalage.info&lt;/a&gt;) a file parser to read a configuration file and the Python library &lt;a href="http://docs.python.org/dev/library/argparse.html" target="_blank" title="argparse"&gt;argparse&lt;/a&gt; for the command line parsing. In addition I have modified the file parser and I've added a "variable container" object, inspired by some snippets found somewhere on the web.  &lt;br&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/posts/python-cli-and-configuration-file-parser.html"&gt;Read more...&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>astro/physics</category><category>code</category><category>Computer</category><category>Master Thesis</category><category>Python</category><category>imported</category><guid>brunetto.github.io/posts/python-cli-and-configuration-file-parser.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 17 Nov 2011 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Python parallel job manager</title><link>brunetto.github.io/posts/python-parallel-job-manager.html</link><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;The final version of the code for my master thesis was the most embarrassing parallel code you can think... just a serial code to be run on different slices of the dataset. I choose this solution because it permits to manage the different resources (memory, processors, ...) on the different machines available without any restriction. Moreover, this solution has no communication between the processes, with better performances and all the processes are independent, so it minimize the damages due to any failure.  &lt;br&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/posts/python-parallel-job-manager.html"&gt;Read more...&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>astro/physics</category><category>code</category><category>Computer</category><category>Master Thesis</category><category>Python</category><category>imported</category><guid>brunetto.github.io/posts/python-parallel-job-manager.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 04 Nov 2011 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>