<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Research on Post It!</title>
    <link>http://brunettoziosi.com/tags/research/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Research on Post It!</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://brunettoziosi.com/tags/research/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Gravitational waves cheat sheet</title>
      <link>http://brunettoziosi.com/posts/gw-cheat-sheet/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brunettoziosi.com/posts/gw-cheat-sheet/</guid>
      <description>I would like to share few notes, a cheat sheet, about gravitational waves I put together while writing a chapter of my PhD thesis and preparing for the PhD school internal exam. I did it to tidy up the mess of references and equations you may find around that never agree and has a terrible notation!!
Here the equations, below the images of the papers.
General introduction Consider a small perturbation of the flat cartedian metric</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PDF manipulation</title>
      <link>http://brunettoziosi.com/posts/pdf-manipulation/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brunettoziosi.com/posts/pdf-manipulation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It happens, from time to time, that I find myself looking for a way to manipulate PDF
on the fly. For example, I want to print them two-pages per sheet, or to extract
few pages, or to shrink the size of the file without degradate the quality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Not only Big Data</title>
      <link>http://brunettoziosi.com/posts/not-only-big-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brunettoziosi.com/posts/not-only-big-data/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently I&amp;rsquo;ve been at a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cineca.it/en&#34;&gt;Cineca&lt;/a&gt; workshop focused on tools to deal with big data analysis.
We had a taste of MapReduce/Hadoop/Spark and friends and we used Docker.
I wrote a small presentation to update my collegues and it become a in-progress presentation of the tools I think are
useful in our everyday work. This presentation aims of acting both as a showcase of what can help us and as a cheat sheet.
You can find it after the break.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Python plot examples</title>
      <link>http://brunettoziosi.com/posts/python-plot-examples/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brunettoziosi.com/posts/python-plot-examples/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Two examples on how to make plots with &lt;a href=&#34;http://home.gna.org/veusz&#34;&gt;Veusz&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&#34;http://matplotlib.org&#34;&gt;Matplotlib&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
I prefer Veusz because it&amp;rsquo;s easier to configure, modify and it produces
perfect &lt;code&gt;pdf&lt;/code&gt; plots, but sometimes Matplotlib it&amp;rsquo;s faster for producing just
a draft plot to inspect data!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Eating</title>
      <link>http://brunettoziosi.com/pages/research/fit/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brunettoziosi.com/pages/research/fit/</guid>
      <description>SciKit Generalized Linear Models  Linear least-squares fits with errors in both coordinates.  PH291-Dual-Axis-Error-Calculation IDL function Weighted least-squares curve fitting with errors in all variables
Gaussian processes / variograms / Kriging http://www.ambhas.com/tools/html/krige_8py_source.html
 http://hpgl.aoizora.org/index.php?option=com_content&amp;amp;view=article&amp;amp;id=47&amp;amp;Itemid=56
 http://blog.technokrat.nl/?p=409 (qui usano la versione R in python)
 https://github.com/scikit-learn/scikit-learn/pull/14
 http://nbviewer.ipython.org/github/fonnesbeck/Bios366/blob/master/notebooks/Section5_1-Gaussian-Processes.ipynb (gaussian processes è il nome ufficiale e generico degli algoritmi tipo quelli di krige)
 http://girs.googlecode.com/svn/trunk/maths/kriging/kriging.py
 http://scikit-learn.org/0.11/auto_examples/gaussian_process/plot_gp_regression.html
 http://www.gaussianprocess.org/</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>StarLab (GPU) old guide</title>
      <link>http://brunettoziosi.com/pages/research/utils/starlab-gpu-old-guide/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brunettoziosi.com/pages/research/utils/starlab-gpu-old-guide/</guid>
      <description>Click here for the new guide!!!
To install CUDA you can try with the CUDA packages in the Ubuntu repositories. If they fail, you have to download CUDA from ****
To locate the CUDA files you can try:
 locate cuda | grep nvcc locate cuda | grep include locate cuda | grep include | grep toolkit (for the SDK files of the new release) locate cuda | grep lib | grep cudaart  Sapporo  in setup_sapporo.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research</title>
      <link>http://brunettoziosi.com/pages/research/research/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brunettoziosi.com/pages/research/research/</guid>
      <description>PhD Project The impact of stellar evolution and dynamics on the formation of compact-object binaries
During my PhD I was part of Dr. Mapelli&amp;rsquo;s research group working on N-body simulations of young and dense star clusters in order to understand the impact of stellar evolution and dynamics on the formation and evolution of compact-object (neutron stars and black holes) binary systems.
These objects are thought to be the best candidates to produce gravitational waves observable in the near future with the second-generation ground-based gravitational wave interferometers Advanced Ligo and Virgo.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>From .csv to HDF5 in Python</title>
      <link>http://brunettoziosi.com/posts/from-csv-to-hdf5-in-python/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Dec 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brunettoziosi.com/posts/from-csv-to-hdf5-in-python/</guid>
      <description>PyTables is a Python library that provide a simple but really useful interface to manage the HDF5 files with some other interesting features (compression, optimizations, &amp;hellip;). To the library presentation and documentation, for now refers, to the site.
I used it a lot during my master thesis to manage the dataset from the Millennium database.
Here I provide a brief review of how I used it to store data obtained in .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Python slicing, rebinning and indexing</title>
      <link>http://brunettoziosi.com/posts/python-slicing-rebinning-and-indexing/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Nov 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brunettoziosi.com/posts/python-slicing-rebinning-and-indexing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;During my master thesis I had to manage a lot of (different) data from GIF and GIF2 projects, Millimillennium, Millenium and Millennium 2 simulations and so on. Sometimes there were the need to sort, divide or rearrange these dataset.&lt;br /&gt;
Here some examples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Python CLI and configuration file parser</title>
      <link>http://brunettoziosi.com/posts/python-cli-and-configuration-file-parser/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Nov 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brunettoziosi.com/posts/python-cli-and-configuration-file-parser/</guid>
      <description>One of the first things I needed writing the code for my thesis was the ability to read options and parameters both from a configuration file and from the command line. After some attempts I have found (at http://www.decalage.info) a file parser to read a configuration file and the Python library argparse for the command line parsing. In addition I have modified the file parser and I&amp;rsquo;ve added a &amp;ldquo;variable container&amp;rdquo; object, inspired by some snippets found somewhere on the web.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>