<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Docker on Post It!</title>
    <link>http://brunettoziosi.eu/tags/docker/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Docker on Post It!</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 16 Jun 2015 10:55:02 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://brunettoziosi.eu/tags/docker/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Install Docker</title>
      <link>http://brunettoziosi.eu/posts/docker-installation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jun 2015 10:55:02 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brunettoziosi.eu/posts/docker-installation/</guid>
      <description>What is Docker? In short:
 &amp;ldquo;An open source project to pack, ship and run any application as a lightweight container.&amp;rdquo;
 In practice Docker
 povide an isolated sharable environment (dev and ship) allow to change dev env without messing-up the host OS ease an app installation is based on lxc (linux containers) and Go remove the need of a virtual machines, it can be used in a similar way but it is different → much more lightweight is (quite) secure (everything is sandboxed), though I don&amp;rsquo;t like its process run as root allow you to commit changes is based on images and containers: templates and running instances (that lose memory on shutdown  I don&amp;rsquo;t want to write an essay on Docker, just present it briefly and describe the best (in my opinion) way to install it on *buntu.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Not only Big Data</title>
      <link>http://brunettoziosi.eu/posts/not-only-big-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brunettoziosi.eu/posts/not-only-big-data/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently I&amp;rsquo;ve been at a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cineca.it/en&#34;&gt;Cineca&lt;/a&gt; workshop focused on tools to deal with big data analysis.
We had a taste of MapReduce/Hadoop/Spark and friends and we used Docker.
I wrote a small presentation to update my collegues and it become a in-progress presentation of the tools I think are
useful in our everyday work. This presentation aims of acting both as a showcase of what can help us and as a cheat sheet.
You can find it after the break.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>