<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Phd on Post It!</title>
    <link>http://brunettoziosi.eu/categories/phd/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Phd on Post It!</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 06 May 2014 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://brunettoziosi.eu/categories/phd/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Poster Making</title>
      <link>http://brunettoziosi.eu/pages/research/postermaking/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brunettoziosi.eu/pages/research/postermaking/</guid>
      <description> http://colinpurrington.com/tips/academic/posterdesign http://colinpurrington.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/09/scientific-poster-advice-purrington.pdf http://www.bioinformaticszen.com/post/genotype-from-phenotype/ http://zachholman.com/posts/slide-design-for-developers/ http://www.colormatters.com/color-and-design/basic-color-theory http://f1000.com/posters/browse?docTypeSearch=Poster  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>GW links</title>
      <link>http://brunettoziosi.eu/pages/research/gw-links/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brunettoziosi.eu/pages/research/gw-links/</guid>
      <description>List of useful links about gravitational waves:
 Gravitational waves detector and sources interactive plot Black hole hunter EGO - European Gravitational Observatory VIRGO LIGO - Laser Interferometer Gravitational Wave Observatory eLISA - Evolved Laser Interferometer Space Antenna AURIGA MiniGRAIL - Gravitational Radiation Antenna In Leiden IPTA - International Pulsar Timing Array EPTA - The European Pulsar Timing Array E-Book on gravitational wave detection Games for science teaching, outreach and research Christopher Berry hompage MatchedFiltering ipython notebook with wave amplitude The First Two Years of Electromagnetic Follow-Up with Advanced LIGO and Virgo  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PhD Project</title>
      <link>http://brunettoziosi.eu/pages/research/phd/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brunettoziosi.eu/pages/research/phd/</guid>
      <description>The impact of stellar evolution and dynamics on the formation of compact-object binaries
My PhD project is devoted to improving our knowledge on the demographics and the properties of double compact-objects (DCO) binaries, i.e. black hole-black hole (BH-BH), neutron star-neutron star (NS-NS) and neutron star-black hole (NS-BH) binaries, inside young dense star clusters. The goal is to derive accurate predictions for the ground-based Advanced Virgo/LIGO gravitational wave detectors sources. Gravitational waves (GWs) are among the ``most wanted&amp;rdquo; predictions of General Relativity: while indirect confirmations of GWs came from observations of pulsar binaries, a direct detection of GWs is still missing.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>StarLab (GPU) old guide</title>
      <link>http://brunettoziosi.eu/pages/research/utils/starlab-gpu-old-guide/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brunettoziosi.eu/pages/research/utils/starlab-gpu-old-guide/</guid>
      <description>Click here for the new guide!!!
To install CUDA you can try with the CUDA packages in the Ubuntu repositories. If they fail, you have to download CUDA from ****
To locate the CUDA files you can try:
 locate cuda | grep nvcc locate cuda | grep include locate cuda | grep include | grep toolkit (for the SDK files of the new release) locate cuda | grep lib | grep cudaart  Sapporo  in setup_sapporo.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>AstroFelpa</title>
      <link>http://brunettoziosi.eu/pages/research/astrofelpa/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brunettoziosi.eu/pages/research/astrofelpa/</guid>
      <description>License 
AstroFelpa by BrunettoZiosi is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 Unported License.
Permissions beyond the scope of this license may be available at www.brunettoziosi.eu/stories/research/astrofelpa.html.
Shop available now!!! You can purchase the t-shirt and other material from here
AstroP(h)D AstroFelpa is an indipendent initiative with the purpose to represent the Padua astronomers and all their friends and supporters.
AstroP(h)D was born within the astronomy PhD students community of Padua but also covers all the astro-workers of the University and the Observatory.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research</title>
      <link>http://brunettoziosi.eu/pages/research/research/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brunettoziosi.eu/pages/research/research/</guid>
      <description>PhD Project The impact of stellar evolution and dynamics on the formation of compact-object binaries
During my PhD I was part of Dr. Mapelli&amp;rsquo;s research group working on N-body simulations of young and dense star clusters in order to understand the impact of stellar evolution and dynamics on the formation and evolution of compact-object (neutron stars and black holes) binary systems.
These objects are thought to be the best candidates to produce gravitational waves observable in the near future with the second-generation ground-based gravitational wave interferometers Advanced Ligo and Virgo.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My favourite PhD Comics</title>
      <link>http://brunettoziosi.eu/pages/personal/my-favourite-phd-comics/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brunettoziosi.eu/pages/personal/my-favourite-phd-comics/</guid>
      <description> PhD Comics Archive Most Popular Marriage vs PhD Motivation Level Thesis Outline The Thesis repulsor field The Thesis title Your computer desktop Ninjas vs Professors Desk entropy &amp;ldquo;Final&amp;rdquo;.doc  </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>